A Guide to the Maupin family papers, 1780-1955 (bulk 1870-1955)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Maupin family papers, 1780-1955 (bulk 1870-1955)
Library of Virginia
37983
2.25 cubic feet (5 boxes).
Maupin family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased
Biographical Information
The Maupin family were residents of Albemarle County and Portsmouth, Virginia, and Baltimore. Dr. Socrates Maupin was born on 25 November 1808. He was a professor of chemistry at Hampden-Sydney College, and later head of the Richmond Academy. He aided in the establishment of the Richmond Medical College. For fifteen years he was associated with the University of Virginia, where he served as President of the Faculty. On 14 December 1837 he married Sally Hay Travis Washington (1812-1891) a daughter of Lund Washington and Susan Monroe Grayson. Dr. Socrates Maupin died in a runaway accident in Lynchburg on 19 October 1871.
His son Chapman Maupin was born in Albemarle County on 23 April 1846. He graduated from the University of Virginia, studied abroad for a few years, and then moved to Maryland where he was made principal of the Baltimore City College, and later founded Maupin's University School in Ellicott City, Maryland. On 5 January 1871 he married Margaret Lewis Taliaferro (1846-1930), a daughter of Gen. Alexander Galt Taliaferro of Annandale, Culpeper County. Chapman Maupin died in Ellicott City, Maryland on 25 July 1900.
Chapman Maupin and his wife had three daughters. They were Agnes Marshall Maupin (1871-1904), Sally Washington Maupin (1874-1944), and Margaret Lewis Maupin (b. 1877) who married Rex Corbin Spencer Maupin. Margaret Lewis Maupin was very active in the Maryland Daughters of the American Revolution and the United Daughters of the Confederacy. She died on 23 September 1955.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1780-1955, of the Maupin family of Albemarle County and Portsmouth, Virginia, and Baltimore, Maryland. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1870 to 1955. Includes correspondence, subject files, and oversized items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Subject files
Series III: Oversize items
Contents List
- Correspondence 1819-1955, 2 boxes (Box 1-2)
  The correspondence between the years 1845 and 1870 deal with Dr. Maupin's work at the University of Virginia. Subjects include appointments and recommendations of faculty members, letters of introduction for various students, including the son of Senator David Levy Yulee of Florida, and other news relating to the university. There are also letters between members of the Maupin family and others discussing national politics and family matters. There is an extensive letter which relates to the future military career of Robert Washington Maupin, and his interest in serving in Peru. The correspondence from this time period also includes letters written to Peter Grayson Washington while he was serving as Assistant Secretary of State which deal with recommendations, appointments, and meetings.
  he correspondence from 1870 to 1900 concerns Champman Maupin and his family. There are letters of sympathy after the death of Dr. Socrates Maupin, letters from Chapman's brother Robert Washington Maupin while a business school student in Baltimore, as well as correspondence involving estate matters, including the sale of lands owned in Wisconsin, Minnesota, and Texas, the destruction and restoration of the Grayson family burial ground at "Bel Aire" estate near Woodbridge in Prince William County, as well as other family matters, genealogical subjects, travels, health, weather, and information relating to Chapman's operation of Maupin's University School in Ellicott City, Maryland.
  After 1900, the letters are written mostly to Margaret Lewis Maupin from her mother and sisters, containing family news. Also ncluded is a letter of sympathy after the death of her sister Agnes Marshall Maupin, Margaret's marriage to Rex Corbin Spencer Maupin and subsequent letters from her husband, and annual dues notices and correspondence from various patriotic organizations.
  - Correspondence 1819 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1837 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1845, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1850-1859 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1860, 1866-1868 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1870-1874 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1875-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 1880-1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence 1890-1893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence 1894-1896 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence 1897 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence 1900 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence 1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence 1902-1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence 1910-1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 2 boxes (Box 3-4)
  The subject files contain accounts and receipts, booklets, a Civil War letter dated 14 August 1864, clippings, genealogical notes and charts, two obituaries, pamphlets, photographs, publications, speeches, a copy of the will of William Maupin dated 1813, and miscellaneous items.
  - Accounts and Receipts (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Agreement, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Booklet--Ambler, Lucy Johnston. When Tidewater Invaded the Valley: A Tribute to the Men of Lower Virginia in the Days of the John Brown Raid, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Booklet--Commemorative Exercises in Honor of the Barlett Statue of Benjamin Franklin, Baltimore, 9 April 1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Booklet--Memory Quotations from English Classic Authors (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Booklet--Sigillologia: Being Some Account of the Great or Broad Seal of the Confederate States of America, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Booklet--Washington Custis Chapter, Daughters of the American Revolution, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Call Slips--Library of Congress (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Calling and Membership Cards (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Christmas, Greeting, and Sympathy Cards (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Civl War Letter, 14 August 1864 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clipped Signatures (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Envelopes (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
  - Extracts from Proceedings of UVA Faculty, 29 May 1878 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Genealogical Chart--Bransford (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Genealogical Chart--Spencer-Maupin (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Genealogical Notes--Burwell (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Genealogical Notes--Chapman (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Genealogical Notes--Cooke (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Genealogical Notes--James (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Genealogical Notes--Maupin (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Genealogical Notes--Murat (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Genealogical Notes--Spencer (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Genealogical Notes--Taliaferro (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Genealogical Notes--Throckmorton (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Genealogical Notes--Townshend (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Genealogical Notes--Washington (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Genealogical Notes The Washington Family and Two Branches, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Genealogical Notes--Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Latin Exercises, 1861-1862 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Marriage Announcement of Margaret Lewis Maupin and Rex Corbin Spencer, 7 November 1917 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Military Pass, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Norfolk-Tidewater Committee of the Colonial Dames of America in the State of Virginia--Membership List, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Obituary of James Rawlings Maupin (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Obituary of Margaret Lewis Maupin, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Order of LaFayette--Constitution, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlet--The Final Solution of the Lee Chapel Problem, Washington and Lee Bulletin, volume XXII, no. 4, 25 March 1923 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlet--The Order of the Service for the Massing of the Colors and Observance of the 208th Birthday of George Washington, the Pro-Cathedral, Baltimore, 18 February 1940 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlet--The People-An Address Delivered Before the Jefferson Literary Society of the University of Virginia in the Public Hall, June 28, 1866 by John W. Daniel of Lynchburg, Va. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlet--Virginia Bill of Rights and 1830 State Constitution (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pedigree of Margaret Lewis Maupin (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Photograph Frames (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Plats and Surveys (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Program--Dedication of the Double Equestrian Statue of Lee and Jackson, Wyman Park, Baltimore, 1 May 1948 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Publications--Jefferson County Historical Society Magazine, volume VII, December 1947 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Publications--The Maryland Society of the Colonial Dames in America, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Publications--University of Virginia Alumni News, volume XII, no. 1, August 1923 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Publications--The Valentine Museum Bulletin, Fall 1951 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Publications--Virginia Drama News, volume XVI, no. 3, 15 December 1947 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Publications--Yorkshire as the Home of the Washingtons (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Poetry (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Reommendation of R. W. Jones as Professor of Physical Science, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Resolutions Passed by Various Institutions Upon the Death of Dr. Socrates Maupin, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Speech--Baltimore Chapter UDC, 23 October 1931 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Speech--Children of the Republic, 17 June 1922 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Speech--Socrates Maupin, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Speech--30th Anniversary of the Washington-Custis Chapter, DAR, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Speeches--Chapman Maupin (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Stock Buys and Sells, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Tax Due Statements (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Will of William Maupin (copy), 1813 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Oversize Items, 1 box (Box 5)
  The oversized items include two deeds, a membership certificate to the Order of LaFayette, a pedigree and genealogical chart, and a sectional map of the cities of Superior, WI and Duluth, MN (1876).
  - Deed, 1780 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Deed, 1808 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Order of LaFayette Membership Certificate, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pedigree of Margaret Lewis Maupine and Via Family Genealogical Chart (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sectional Map of Cities of Superior, Wisconsin, and Duluth, Minnesota, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 5)